Canadian American Women's Committee Records, 1941-1969
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Canadian-American Women's Committee records
1941-1969
Canadian American Women's Committee
MS 355
13 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Canadian-American Women's Committee was founded as an international organization with the aim of developing appreciation and cooperation between the two countries through increased knowledge. Records of the American Section and the Connecticut Branch include material on conferences, field study trips, affiliation with the National Council of Women, student exchanges, and administrative records.
Vera Beggs and Cairine Wilson believed that the practical international cooperation between Canada and the U.S. developed during World War I could not be trusted to extend into the future solely through treaties and joint boards. In 1941, they founded the Canadian-American Women's Committee, an international organization with the aim of developing appreciation and cooperation between the two countries through increased knowledge. The Committee was composed of two sections. The Canadian division had headquarters in Ottawa, while the its American counterpart was based in New York. Each operated separately to suit their activities to the situation of their respective countries, and joint international conferences of Committee leaders were held to determine general policies. In both countries, the Committee worked a great deal with national women's organizations. In addition, it sponsored educational conferences, field study trips for college students and teachers, student exchanges, teacher exchanges, and lecture tours. Though the Canadian Section disbanded in 1966 and the American section disbanded in 1969, the group established permanent student exchanges.
The Canadian-American Women's Committee Records consist of 5 linear feet of the records of the American Section and the Connecticut Branch. They contain material on conferences, field study trips (itineraries, student notes, and records regarding class activities), affiliation with the National Council of Women, student exchanges, and administrative records. Types of materials include clippings; publications, such as newsletters and pamphlets for conferences; correspondence; reports; financial records; minutes; and speech texts. Also included is correspondence concerning programs to foster mutual appreciation, cooperation, and communication (such as an art exchange between school-children).
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Subjects
II. American Section
III. Connecticut Branch
IV. Student Exchanges
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
The Canadian American Women's Committee Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by May Hall James.
Recent additions to this collection are unprocessed and are not reflected in the finding aid.
Search Terms
Student exchange programs--Canada--History--Sources; United States--Relations--Canada; Women-International cooperation--History--Sources; James, May Hall; Beggs, Vera W. (Vera Wadsworth), d. 1968; Canadian-American Women's Committee--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional records of the Connecticut branch of the Canadian American Women's Committee are at the Schlesinger Library, Harvard University.
- SERIES I. SUBJECTS
  - AAUW Conference (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Exchange (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Canadian tour, Willimantic (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chautauqua meeting (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Canadian section
    - Addresses of members (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Canadian Institute of Public Affairs (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Canadians (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cairine R. Wilson: correspondence, photograph (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Newsletters (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Conference on Canada, 1964-65 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Conferences, general, 1943-49 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1942-65 (Box 3, Folder 15-25)
  - Correspondence, official, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence re: published materials on Canada, 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Field Study course to Canada, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Field Study course to Canada (trans-Canada air tour), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Fifteenth anniversary, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Financial records (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Hall, May James, photo (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - History (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - History, original meeting (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - League college project (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - MacSkimming visit (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Manuscript materials and miscellaneous clippings (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous material (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Nursery education project (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Project in international hospitality (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Publications (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Small informal group meetings (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Survey of teaching about Canada in American Schools (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Teacher exchange program (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Twentieth anniversary (Box 5, Folder 45)
- SERIES II. AMERICAN SECTION
  - Chronological files, 1943-1969 (Box 6, Folder 46-54)
  - Subject files
    - Activities, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Addresses of members (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Art teacher grants, 1960, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 57-58)
    - By-laws (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Correspondence, 1949-50 (Box 6, Folder 60-61)
    - Correspondence and reports, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Education re: Canada (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - James, May Hall, first trip to Canada, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Meetings, major, 1951-59 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Membership lists (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - New York group, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Newsletters (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Official publications (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Quebec, Montreal Conference, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Sophia Smith Collection (Box 7, Folder 70a)
    - Transfer of headquarters (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1949-67 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - National Council of Women in the United States (part of American Section).
    - General (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Hospitality Committee (Box 8, Folder 74)
- SERIES III. CONNECTICUT BRANCH
  - Chronological files, 1946-1964 (Box 9, Folder 75-78)
  - Art grants (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Correspondence, minutes, reports, 1943-44 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1945-49 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - James, May Hall, trip to Canada, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Special records (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Study guide on Canada (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Traveling library (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1944-67 (Box 9, Folder 86)
- SERIES IV. STUDENT EXCHANGES
  - Chronological files, 1844-1957 (Box 10, Folder 87-98)
  - Toronto-Smith exchange
    - Correspondence, 1945-67 (Box 11, Folder 99-100)
    - Newsletters, "The Journal" (Smith student experiences), 1953-65 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - Chronological files, 1960-1969 (Box 12, Folder 102-106)
  - Subject files
    - Address list (Box 13, Folder 107)
    - Alberta--Central Connecticut, 1945-50 (Box 13, Folder 108)
    - Alberta--First exchange, 1951-2 (Box 13, Folder 109)
    - Alberta--TCC exchange, 1953, 1954, 1955, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 110)
    - Central Connecticut State College (Box 13, Folder 111)
    - Danbury State Teachers College (Box 13, Folder 112)
    - Douglas College (Box 13, Folder 113)
    - Evaluation (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - General (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - Saskatchewan--Trenton (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - University of Maine (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - Willimantic State Teachers College (Box 13, Folder 118)